Guide to the Robert L. McCaul, Jr. Papers 1900-1994
University of Chicago Library
McCaul, Robert L., Jr. Papers
1900-1994
19 linear feet (38 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Robert L. McCaul, Jr. was Professor of Education at the University of Chicago, and a scholar of John Dewey and of the history of public education in Illinois. The collection contains correspondence, research materials, material regarding the 1969 student sit-in at the University of Chicago, and drafts of several books. Material dates from 1900 to 1994, with the bulk dating between 1963 and 1991.
Information on Use
Access
Material in Series VII, boxes 29-37 is restricted until 2025. Material in box 38 is restricted for 80 years from the date of creation.
Biographical Note
Robert L. McCaul, Jr. was born May 29, 1913 in Waltham, Massachusetts. He studied Classics at Boston College from 1929 to 1932 and then went on to Harvard College where he received his Bachelor's degree in English Language and Literature in 1935. McCaul completed a Master of Education degree at Harvard in 1937 and worked for several years in the Waltham public schools and then at the Laboratory School at the University of Chicago.
In 1940 McCaul married Isabel Ruth Sheehan. The couple had two sons, Robert L. III, Edward, and a daughter Margaret who died in 1974.
From 1946 to 1954 McCaul was Assistant Professor of English at the University of Chicago, and during that time also completed a PhD in History of Education at the University. In 1954 he received an appointment as Assistant Professor in the Department of Education, where he taught until retiring in 1978.
In addition to teaching, McCaul served on the Board of Editors of the School Review from 1962 to 1967 and as Vice-President and President of the History of Education Society from 1965 to 1967.
McCaul's research interests include the early history of American education, the life and work of John Dewey, minorities in American history and American education, power in American society, and the usefulness of newspapers for historical research. Notable publications include The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois, published in 1987, "Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1852-1900," Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1852-1971 (both with Peter DeBoer), and several articles on John Dewey and on education in Colonial Georgia.
McCaul died July 23, 1994 in Chicago.
Scope Note
The collection contains a detailed personal journal, correspondence, research materials, and drafts of several books. It is divided into 7 Series.
Series I, Personal, contains personal items, biographical information and curriculum vitae, arranged alphabetically.
Series II, Correspondence, contains general correspondence, arranged alphabetically by correspondent, and a collection of greeting cards arranged chronologically.
Series III, University of Chicago, contains material from McCaul's time as a professor at the University. It is divided into two subseries. Subseries 1, Administrative, contains memoranda relating to a dean search and other Education Department and general University business. In addition, the series contains collected flyers, newsletters, memoranda, and other material reflecting and discussing the political climate on the U of C campus in the late 1960s. Much of the material has to do with the 1969 student sit-in in the University Administration building, the University's Kalven Report, and subsequent disciplinary actions taken against students. Subseries 2, Teaching, contains course materials – largely reading lists, article photocopies, and bibliographic notes.
Series IV, Research, contains notes, photocopies and transcriptions of source material (mostly correspondence of and concerning John Dewey), and other research materials not housed with particular book or article drafts. It also includes articles by others which clearly related to McCaul's research interests, and the typescripts of two autobiographical works by Margaret A. Haley.
Series V, Writings and Speeches, contains book and article manuscripts, texts of speeches and talks, notes, correspondence relating to specific works, and some research material. Material is arranged alphabetically by the title of the work, and material for each work is arranged chronologically. One of McCaul's large-scale works, The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois, had several working titles. Material relating to this book is labelled and alphabetized according to the working title on the manuscript, typescript, correspondence, or original folder. The final title is also indicated in the folder headings. In many cases, McCaul's files and correspondence merely referred to the work as [The] Struggle for Schooling; material so labelled retains that labelling here.
Series VI, Microfilm, contains a microfilm roll of what appears to be correspondence and portrait photographs of McCaul.
Series VII, Restricted, contains evaluative material pertaining to McCaul's students, restricted for 80 years from date of creation. It also contains McCaul's personal journal: roughly 9 boxes' worth of loose-leaf typed pages and carbon copies detailing his activities and preoccupations as a professor in the mid-1960s. Among the journal pages McCaul placed clippings, booklets, memos, and other materials. The journal is restricted until 2025.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Dewey, John. Collection
Havinghurst, Robert J. Papers
Thelen, Herbert. Papers
University of Chicago. Graduate School of Education. Records
Subject Headings
McCaul, Robert L.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952; University of Chicago. Department of Education; University of Chicago. Graduate School of Education; Education--United States--History--19th century; Education--United States--History--20th century
INVENTORY
- Series I: Personal
  - Clipping – Federal Judges in Chicago, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clipping – Interstate Highways, Note, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Curriculum Vitae and Publications List, 1989, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "A Glance Back at my Journal for 1963-1964," 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - List of Doctoral Committees Chaired, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Nuclear Arms Letter (McCaul, signatory), 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Personal Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Political Mailings and Buttons – 1968 Election, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Political Mailings and Brochures – 1970, 1971, 1972, 1974 Elections, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Political Mailings, 1976-1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - YMCA Vocational Guidance Clinic Brochure, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Correspondence – Bidwell, Charles E., 1975-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence – Borup-Nielsen, Grå, 1986-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence re Dewey, 1959-1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence re Dewey Letters, 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence and Articles – Dykhuizen, George, 1952-1965 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence – Eaton, Bill, 1976-1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence – General, 1957-1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence – General, 1975-1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence – Kaiser, Jill, 1974-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence – Katch, Jed, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence re Old Central High School, Chicago, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence – Urban, Wayne J., 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Greeting Cards and Postcards, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Greeting Cards and Postcards, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Greeting Cards and Postcards, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Greeting Cards and Postcards, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Greeting Cards and Postcards, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Series III: University of Chicago
  - Subseries 1: Administrative
    - Annual Faculty Reports, 1956-1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Committee on Nominating a Chair and Dean – Department of Education – Correspondence, Memoranda and Internal Documents, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Department of Education Memoranda, 1969-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Department of Education – Memoranda – Faculty Deaths, 1968-1977 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Department of Education – Newsletter, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Department of Education Personnel – Memoranda and Caricatures, 1969-1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Laboratory School Memoranda, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Lists of Department of Education PhD Students and Dissertations, 1972, 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Memoranda, Fliers, and Clippings – Politics at the University [1 of 7], 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Memoranda, Fliers, and Clippings – Politics at the University [2 of 7], 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Memoranda, Fliers, and Clippings – Politics at the University [3 of 7], 1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Memoranda, Fliers, and Clippings – Politics at the University [4 of 7], 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Memoranda, Fliers, and Clippings – Politics at the University [5 of 7], 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Memoranda, Fliers, and Clippings – Politics at the University [6 of 7], 1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Memoranda, Fliers, and Clippings – Politics at the University [7 of 7], 1969-1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Summer Study Brochures, 1955-1957 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - The University of Chicago Magazine Vol. 84, No. 1, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - University Memoranda, 1975, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - University Senate Council – Meeting Minutes and Memoranda, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 2: Teaching
    - Education 302 – The History of Western Education – Readings, circa 1977 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Education 316 – Chicago High School Admission Exam, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Education 319 – History of Public and Private Education in Chicago – Reading Lists, Bibliographic Cards, Memos, 1974, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Education 321 – History of American Urban Education – Class Rosters, Course Materials, Discussion Notes, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Education 394 – History of School Administration – Bibliographies, Clippings, 1969-1976 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Education 416 – History of Public Education in Chicago – Outline, Discussion Notes, Reading List, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Education 416 – Studies in the History of Urban Schools – Readings and Clippings, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - History of Urban School Systems – Readings, 1972, 1976, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Shea, Gail – Dissertation Proposal, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Telephone Conversations with Students, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Series IV: Research
  - "An Act Relating to Common Schools in the City of Chicago and for Other Purposes" – Mimeographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Bibliographic Notes, Article, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Black Artists, esp. Edmonia Lewis – Clippings, Correspondence, Brochures, Notes, 1987-1988 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Book Lists, 1957, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Catalogs of Historical Newspapers, 1973, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Civil War and Education – Readings, Bibliographic Notes, Clippings, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Curriculum: Administrator's Notebook Articles, 1965, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Davis, William E. and Edward J. McCaul – "Principals' Attitudes toward Special Education: Issues Concerns, and Training Needs" – Report, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Dewey – Alice C. Dewey Correspondence – Transcriptions, Photocopies, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Dewey – Appointment, Resignation, Aftermath – Notes and Transcriptions, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Dewey as Administrator – Notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Dewey at Johns Hopkins, 1882-1884 – Notes and Transcriptions, Correspondence, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Dewey – Blaine-Harper Correspondence – Transcriptions and Photocopies, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Dewey – Blaine-Harper Correspondence and Phone Messages– Transcriptions and Photocopies, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Dewey – Capps to Harper and Dewey – Transcriptions, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Dewey Correspondence – 1894-1899 – Transcriptions and Photocopies, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Dewey Correspondence – 1900-1902 – Transcriptions and Photocopies, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Dewey Correspondence – 1903-1904 – Transcripts and Photocopies, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Dewey – Correspondence from Harper, 1895-1904 – Transcriptions, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Dewey – Correspondence to Others -- Photocopies, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Dewey – Correspondence with Flora J. Cooke – Photocopies, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Dewey – Correspondence with William James -- Photocopies, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Dewey Correspondence "First Typed Copy," undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Dewey Material (Correspondence and Memoranda) – "Second Typed Copy," undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Dewey – Financial Records – Transcriptions, Photocopies, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Dewey – General Correspondence to Dewey – Transcriptions, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Dewey – Harper Correspondence with Others – Transcriptions [1 of 2], undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Dewey – Harper Correspondence with Others – Transcriptions [2 of 2], undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - "Dewey Leaves Chicago" – Transcriptions of Correspondence, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Dewey – Merger of Chicago Institute and High Schools with University of Chicago – Transcriptions and Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Dewey – Notes, Articles, Correspondence, 1939-1965, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Dewey – Porter-Baber-Cooke Correspondence – Photocopies, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Dewey –Resignation – Photocopies, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Dewey – Statements of Lab School Teachers and Pupils, 1955-1956 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Dewey, "The University School" – Notes, Source Material, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Dewey – Why Biography?" – Transcriptions, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - "Dewey's Chicago" – Transcriptions, undated (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - The Elementary School Record, Nos. 3, 9, 1900 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Haley, Margaret A. – Battleground – Typescript Photocopy [1 of 3], undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Haley, Margaret A. – Battleground – Typescript Photocopy [2 of 3], undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Haley, Margaret A. – Battleground – Typescript Photocopy [3 of 3], undated (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Haley, Margaret A. – Correspondence and Chicago Teachers Federation Materials – Photocopies, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Haley, Margaret A. – My Story– Photocopied Fragments, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Haley, Margaret A. – My Story– Typescript Photocopy [1 of 2], undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Haley, Margaret A. – My Story– Typescript Photocopy [2 of 2], undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Population and Education in Illinois – Statistics and Tables, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Population, Black and White, Illinois – Statistics and Tables, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - "Report of the Committee on Schools of the Common Council of the City of Chicago (January 14, 1841)" – Typescripts, undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Review of Educational Research, Vol. XXV, No. 1, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Review of Educational Research, Vol. XXVI, No. 3, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - School Reform – Reports and Bibliographic Notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Teacher Recruitment and Clinic Booklets, 1957 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Wechsler, Harold S. – "A History of School Review" Parts I and II – Reprints, 1979-1980 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Series V: Writings and Speeches
  - The American Educational Tradition – Chapter I, Colonial Period – Typescript, Document Transcriptions, Correspondence [1 of 2], 1960, undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - The American Educational Tradition – Chapter I, Colonial Period – Typescript and Document Transcriptions, [2 of 2], undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - The American Educational Tradition – Chapter I, Colonial Period – Typescript Carbon Copies, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - The American Educational Tradition – Chapter I, Conclusion – Typescript, Notes, Bibliography, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - The American Educational Tradition – Correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - The American Educational Tradition – Expenses, 1960-1963 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - The American Educational Tradition – Outline and Reviewers' Comments, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - "American Elementary and Secondary Education: Plus and Minus" (Fulbright Talk) – Program Only, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - The American Tradition in Education: History and Documents – Outlines, Typescript Fragment (Later The American Educational Tradition), undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S. (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Correspondence and Clippings re Research and Funding, 1965-1987 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1852-1971 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – McCaul-De Boer Correspondence, 1966-1975 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1952-1900 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – May 1971 Revision – Typescripts, Correspondence, Clipping [1 of 2], 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1952-1900 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – May 1971 Revision – Typescripts, Correspondence, Clipping [2 of 2], 1971 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1852-1900 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Revision Fragments, circa 1971 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1952-1900 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Parts I, II, and III – Reprints, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S. (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Correspondence, 1975-1992 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1901-1925" (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Typescript, Notes, Correspondence, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - "Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1901-1925" (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Typescripts with Corrections, Correspondence, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S. (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Miscellaneous Expenses, 1986-1987 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1852-1971 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Indices – Correspondence and Corrections, De Boer Typescript, 1987-1991 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1852-1971 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Bound Typescript, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1852-1971 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Bound Proofs, circa 1988 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1852-1971 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Introduction – Typescripts, Correspondence, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1852-1971 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Typescript, Corrections, Correspondence, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1852-1971 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Names-Titles Index – Typescripts with Corrections, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1852-1971 (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Subjects-Issues Index – Carbon Copies, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S. (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Marketing Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S. (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Editorial Tallies, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - "Annotated List of Chicago Tribune Editorials on Elementary and Secondary Education in the U. S., 1901-1925" (Peter P. De Boer and Robert L. McCaul) – Typescript, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling.. .—Discards from 1984 Revision [1 of 2], 1984 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling.. .—Discards from 1984 Revision [1 of 2], 1984 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois – Miscellaneous Expenses and Receipts, 1985-1987 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois – Editing, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois – Correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois – Marked Proof (with Correspondence) [1 of 3], 1986-1987 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois – Marked Proof (with Correspondence) [2 of 3], 1986-1987 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois – Marked Proof (with Correspondence) [3 of 3], 1986-1987 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois – Abstract – Typescripts, 1987 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling in Nineteenth Century Illinois – Sales and Publicity, 1987-1992 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Front matter and Chapter 1, Revision – Photocopy, undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 2 – Photocopy, undated (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 3 – Photocopy, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 4 – Typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 4 – Photocopy, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 5 – Typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 5 – Photocopy, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 6 – Typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 6 – Photocopy, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 7 – Typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 7 – Photocopy, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 8 – Partial Typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 8 – Photocopy, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 9 – Photocopy, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - The Black Struggle for Public Schooling... – Chapter 9 – Photocopy, undated (Box 13, Folder 13)